Spiro, Eugen; Papers ger086
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Eugen Spiro Papers
1940-1972
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger086
3 cubic ft.
German-Jewish painter interned in the French concentration camp at Gurs, painted portraits of Thomas Mann, Albert Einstein, and other notables. The collection includes correspondence, photographs of Spiro's artwork, and exhibit catalogues.
Biographical History
Eugen(e) Spiro, portrait and landscape painter, graphic artist and illustrator, is best known for his portraits of European personalities (incl. Thomas Mann, Theodor Heuss, Albert Bassermann, Fritz von Unruh, and his first wife Tilla Durieux), American personalities (incl. Archbishop Edward Cardinal Mooney, Judge M. J. Proskauer and George N. Shuster), and famous musicians (incl. Richard Strauss, Bruno Walter, Arturo Toscanini, Bronislaw Hubermann and Gregor Piatigorsky). Perhaps his most well-known portrait is his 1941 rendering of the émigré physicist Albert Einstein. His paintings hang in many museums worldwide including the National Galerie in Berlin, the Musée Nationale d'Art Moderne in Paris, the Bezelle Museum in Jerusalem and the Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Spiro was born in Breslau, Germany, on April 18, 1874, the son of a cantor, Abraham Beer, and his wife, Fanny Form Spiro, and one of nine children. He studied art in Breslau under Albrecht Bräuer and later became a master student of Franz von Stuck in Munich. His early portraits of women appeared frequently in, as well as on the covers of, the Jugendstil magazine, Der Jugend. After a brief marriage to the actress Tilla Durieux (1904-1906), Spiro relocated to Paris where he studied the French masters and impressionists, became a Professor at the Académie Moderne, co-founded the Salon d'Automne, and belonged to the circle of artists and writers of the Parisian Café du Dôme.
In 1914, Spiro returned to Berlin where he became Chairman of the Berliner Sezession and a Professor at the Berlin Academy of Arts. He remained in Berlin until Hitler's rise to power in 1933, when he was forbidden to work because of his Jewish background. He voluntarily resigned from his posts in 1934, secured a visa, and was allowed to immigrate to Paris in 1935. Spiro remained in Paris for the next five years, operating as a freelance artist, painting portraits and giving private lessons, participating in exhibits in Amsterdam and London. Together with other immigrants he founded, became co-director and first chairman of the Union des Artistes libres in Paris.
With the spread of the Hitler's influence to France in 1940, Spiro was again forced to flee, this time via Spain and Portugal, arriving in the United States in 1941 at the age of 67, a relatively unknown artist in America. Spiro, a well-known artist in Europe, had asked Albert Einstein years earlier to sit for a portrait. At the time, Einstein had replied that he would sit only for unknown artists. After Spiro's arrival in the U.S. in 1941, he once again approached Einstein to sit for a portrait, this time as a newly arrived émigré and an unknown artist in his newly adopted homeland. This time Einstein agreed and Spiro painted his well-known portrait of the physicist.
Eugen Spiro was married three times: first to actress Tilla Durieux (1904-1906), second to Elisabeth Saenger-Sethe in 1917, with whom he had one son, Peter, and lastly to Lilly Jacoby, whom he met in the French internment camp of Gurs in 1940 and married a year later. The couple settled in New York in 1941. Spiro lived to the age of 98 and died in New York City on September 26, 1972.
1874 Born on April 18, in Breslau, Germany, one of nine children of the Jewish cantor, Abraham Beer and his wife, Fanny Form Spiro.
1880-1892 Attended the Elisabeth-Gymnasium, Breslau.
1892 Apprenticeship in fashion design with a ladies garment firm.
1892-1894 Attended Royal School of Arts, Breslau; studied under Albrecht Bräuer.
1894-1897 Attended the Academy of Arts in Munich, studied under Franz von Stuck.
1897-1898 Study trip to Italy with the Saxon school.
1899-1904 Teacher and portrait painter in Breslau; contributed to Jugendstil journal Jugend; first series of portraits of musicians.
1900 Became member of Münchner Sezession.
1904 Moved to Berlin.
1904-1906 Married to actress Tilla Durieux.
1906 Became a member of Berliner Sezession; participated in exhibits, including Wiener Sezession; moved to Paris.
1906-1914 Professor at the Académie Moderne and co-founder of the Salon d'Automne, Paris; belonged to circle of artists and writers of the Café du Dôme; copied French masters and impressionists.
1914 Returned to Berlin.
1914-1933 Member of the executive board, and President of the Berliner Sezession. Professor at the Academy of Arts, Berlin.
1915-1917 Served in the cartographic department of the German general staff.
1917 Married Elisabeth Saenger-Sethe, with whom he had one son, Peter. Professor at the Staatliche Kunstschule in Berlin.
1921 Study trip to Italy.
1924-1933 Chairman of the United Artists' Corporation (Kartell der Vereinigten Bildenden Künstler Berlins).
1927-1933 Member of the Experts' and Purchase Committees of the Nationalgalerie Berlin and other German museums.
1929 First trip to United States; exhibited his work at the Carnegie Institute in Pittsburgh, PA.
1933 Prohibited from working by Hitler; voluntary resignation from all honorary posts.
1935 Left Germany in September and immigrated to Paris (with visa).
1935-1940 Freelance artist in Paris, painting portraits and giving private lessons; participated in exhibits in Amsterdam, London; co-director and first chairman of Union des Artistes libres.
1936 Resigned his German citizenship.
1940 Not interned because of age; fled with family to Marseilles via Nantes, Biarritz and Pau; met future third wife, Lilly Jacoby in French concentration camp Gurs.
1940-1941 Emigration to the United States via Spain and Portugal.
1941 Arrived in the U.S. in Baltimore, MD on May 18; moved to New York in May; married Lilly Jacoby on September 30.
1943 First individual exhibit at the Galerie St. Etienne, New York, where he would exhibit seven times, the last exhibit on the occasion of his 90th birthday in 1964.
1948-1952 Teacher at the Wayman Adams School, Elizabethtown, NY.
1952 First post-war visit to the Federal Republic of Germany.
1957 First post-war exhibit in the Federal Republic of Germany at the Gallerie Wolfgang Gurlitt in Munich.
1964 Awarded Das Grosse Verdienstkreuz from the Federal Republic of Germany.
1969 Retrospective exhibit in honor of Spiro's 95th birthday at the Berlin Museum.
1972 Died in New York City on September 26 at the age of 98.
Scope and Contents
The Eugen Spiro Papers consist of 3 cubic feet of materials, 1903-1985, and include 1 cu. ft. of correspondence of Eugen Spiro and his wife, Lilly. Although there is some correspondence with friends, most of the correspondence relates to Spiro's artwork, including letters from many of the individuals he sketched (Thomas Mann, Albert Einstein, Theodor Heuss, and numerous prominent musicians). The collection also contains photographs of Spiro's artwork, either in private ownership or in museums, as well as catalogs of his exhibitions, especially with the Galerie St. Etienne in New York City.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into seven series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1903-1913, 1941-1985
Series 2: Biographical materials and documents
Series 3: Writings of Eugen Spiro, 1932-1964, undated
Series 4: Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his artwork; catalogs of exhibits, 1903-1978
Series 5: Reproductions and photographs of Eugen Spiro's artwork, 1905-1979
Series 6: Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and friends, 1941-1978, undated
Series 7: Miscellaneous materials
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, in June 1986.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Art; Artists -- Germany.; Artists -- United States.; Concentration camps -- France.; Portrait painting, German.; Germans -- France.; Berlin (Germany) -- Jews.; Concentration camps -- France -- Gurs.; Spiro, Eugen, 1874-1972.; Sprio, Lilli.; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955.; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955.
- Correspondence, 1903-1913; 1941-1985; 1; 120 file folders
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged in three sub-series: general correspondence of Eugen Spiro, 1903-1913 and 1941-1972; correspondence with owners and subjects of Spiro paintings; and correspondence of Lilly Spiro, primarily dating from the years after Eugen's death, 1972-1985. Among the noteworthy correspondents are: Tilla Durieux, Albert Einstein, George Grosz, Theodor Heuss, Otto Loewi, Thomas Mann, Dimitri Mitropoulos, Albert Schweitzer and Gottfried Reinhard Treviranus.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - General correspondence of Eugen Spiro (after 1972, with Lilly Spiro), 1960-1969; 1.1
    - Adler, Karl, 1960-1962 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 1)
    - Alexander, Eugen, 1943 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 2)
    - Amt für Kunst Zehlendorf, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 3)
    - Artist Publishing Co Ltd., 1961 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 4)
    - Artist Research Project, The City College, 1955 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 5)
    - Artists Equity Association (AEA), 1954 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 6)
    - Berlin Museum (Irmgard Wirth), 1969-1985 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 7)
    - Bertram, Else, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 8)
    - The Bezalel National Museum, Jerusalem, 1959 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 9)
    - Bezirksamt Tiergarten zu Berlin, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 10)
    - Brüning, Heinrich, 1945; photocopy (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 11)
    - Bülow-Galerie, Berlin, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 12)
    - The Busoni Society, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 13)
    - Colm, Gerhard, 1944 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 14)
    - Columbia Artists Management, Inc., 1953 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 15)
    - Conference on Jewish Material Claims Against Germany, Inc. / Memorial Foundation for Jewish Culture, 1966-1984 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 16)
    - Corinth, Thomas, 1969; 1979 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 17)
    - Deutsche Generalkonsul, 1964-1980 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 18)
    - Deutsche Museen (German museums, general), 1963-1969 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 19)
    - Deutsches Museum, München, 1955-1957 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 20)
    - Dodd, Mead & Company, 1952 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 21)
    - Durieux, Tilla, 1954; 1956; photocopies (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 22)
    - Einstein, Albert, 1941-1942; photocopies (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 23)
    - Entschädigungsamt Berlin, 1966-1985 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 24)
    - Fürst, Gerhard, 1955-1960 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 25)
    - Galerie St. Etienne, 1964; 1979 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 26)
    - George, Manfred (Aufbau), 1953 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 27)
    - Germanisches Nationalmuseum, Nürnberg, 1966-1969 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 28)
    - Gesundheit, Betty Rosenthal, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 29)
    - Goethe House, New York, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 30)
    - Grosz, George, 1943; photocopy (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 31)
    - Heuss, Theodor, 1954-1963 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 32)
    - Higgins, Mary B., 1953 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 33)
    - Hoffmann, Eva, 1967 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 34)
    - Holde, Artur, 1950 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 35)
    - Horkheimer, Max, 1943; photocopy (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 36)
    - Hubermann, Bronislaw, Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 37)
    - Hutschnecker, Arnold, 1955-1961; 1979 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 38)
    - The Jewish Museum, Hebrew Union College, 1954-1955 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 39)
    - Knudson, Hans, 1955 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 40)
    - Kunsthalle Bremen (Günter Busch), 1960; 1962 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 41)
    - Lucks, Kai, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 42)
    - Mann, Golo, 1971; photocopy (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 43)
    - Mann, Thomas, 1941; 1950; 1951; photocopies, photographs (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 44)
    - Max Beckmann Gesellschaft, 1967 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 45)
    - Mayer, Hans-Otto, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 46)
    - The Metropolitan Opera Guild, 1951 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 47)
    - Meyer, Hermann, 1967-1968 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 48)
    - Mitropoulos, Dimitri, 1951 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 49)
    - Musician lithographs (general), 1946-1971 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 50)
    - Musikhaus Au Concert, 1967-1968 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 51)
    - Picard, Jacob, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 52)
    - Radio Corporation of America (R.C.A), 1950; 1953 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 53)
    - Redslob, Edwin, 1965; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 54)
    - Reinhardt, Max, 1933; photocopy (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 55)
    - Rembrandt Verlag, Berlin, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 56)
    - Revenaugh, Daniel, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 57)
    - Sachs, Charlotte Cramer, 1951 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 58)
    - Scheyer, Ernst, 1959-1978 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 59)
    - Schiller Nationalmuseum, Marbach, 1968-1969 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 60)
    - Seaman, Julian, 1944 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 61)
    - Shuster, George N., 1945; 1960 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 62)
    - Spencker, Joachim (Carl Hanser Verlag), 1970 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 63)
    - Spiro, Peter, 1969; 1985 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 64)
    - Süddeutscher Verlag (Ludwig Kusche), 1964-1965 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 65)
    - Swarzenski, George, 1942 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 66)
    - Treviranus, G. R., 1945; 1957-1958 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 67)
    - Unruh, Fritz von, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 68)
    - U.S. Treasury Department (re: War Bonds campaign), 1943 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 69)
    - Weltsch, Robert, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 70)
    - Wilhelm-Lehmbruck-Museum der Stadt Duisburg, 1964-1969 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 71)
    - Zaudmer, Ursula, 1949 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 72)
    - Zucker, Paul, 1943 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 73)
    - Early letters, 1903-1913; photocopies (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 74)
    - Miscellaneous letters, 1946-1970 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 75)
    - 75th birthday, 1949 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 76)
    - 80th birthday, 1954 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 77)
    - 85th birthday, 1959 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 78)
    - 90th birthday, A-K, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 79)
    - 90th birthday, L-Z, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 80)
    - 90th birthday, ORT, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 81)
    - 95th birthday, 1969 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 82)
  - Correspondence with owners and subjects of paintings, 1943-1985; 1.2
    - A. von Bethmann-Hollweg Antiquitäten, 1981; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 83)
    - American Committee for the Weizmann Institute of Science (Siegfried Ullmann), 1955; 1958; 1963 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 84)
    - American Council for Emigrés in the Professions (ACEP), 1968 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 84)
    - Archives of American Art, 1977 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 84)
    - Assmann, Leo Robert, 1962 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 85)
    - Buzalski, Ulrich, 1964; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 85)
    - Carnegie Institute of Technology, Department of Fine Arts, 1948 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 85)
    - Consistoire Israelite de Paris (Baron Guy de Rothschild), 1956 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 86)
    - Engel, Max, 1955 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 87)
    - Erkens, August, 1964; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 87)
    - Fenton, Betty & Morris, 1970; photographs (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 87)
    - Firkusny, Rudolf, 1946 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 88)
    - Firle, Tomas, 1969; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 88)
    - Fischbeck, Walter, 1969-1971; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 89)
    - Florian Karsch Galerie Nierendorf, Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 89)
    - Fraenkel, Ernst, 1955-1956 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 90)
    - Friedlaender, Eugen, 1949 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 90)
    - Grosche, Hildegard, 1965; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 90)
    - Grunfeld, Ernst, 1969 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 90)
    - Guttstadt, Riwa & John, Undated; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 90)
    - Hempe, Fritz, 1959-1960 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 91)
    - Hesse, R., 1958 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 91)
    - Heyden, Gunter, 1972; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 91)
    - Hirschel, Hans, 1964; photographs (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 91)
    - Hochschild, Mauricio, 1961 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 92)
    - Horowitz, Wanda T., 1943 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 92)
    - Hussarek, F., 1969; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 92)
    - Jacobson, Gunther, 1943 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 92)
    - Jessner, Elsa, 1958 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 92)
    - Kaiser, J., 1970 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 93)
    - Kempinski, Melanie, Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 93)
    - Klein, Anni, 1966 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 93)
    - Knittl, Andreas, 1960-1961; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 93)
    - Koussevitzky, Serge, 1948 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 94)
    - Kreisler, Fritz, 1945 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 94)
    - Kultusministerium Baden-Württemberg, 1966-1967 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 94)
    - Lamm, Curt & Elena, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 95)
    - Leo Baeck Institute, 1975 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 95)
    - Levy, Erna, 1960; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 95)
    - Lewin, Lola, 1969-1973 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 96)
    - Loewi, Otto, 1954 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 97)
    - Marsh, Elizabeth, 1953 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 97)
    - Musée National d'Art Moderne, Paris, 1954 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 97)
    - Museum der Stadt Karlsruhe, 1959 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 97)
    - Nissen, Rudolph, 1949-1950 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 98)
    - Oppenheimer, Chanan, 1958; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 98)
    - Peerce, Jan, 1944; 1949 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 98)
    - Pinza, Ezio, 1946 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 98)
    - Popper, Kurt S., 1962 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 98)
    - Rosenfeld, I., 1961; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 99)
    - Rosenthal, Theo, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 99)
    - Scherman, Bernadette, 1956 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 99)
    - Schnabel, Artur, 1945 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 99)
    - Schonwald-Pringsheim, Isolde, 1964; photographs (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 100)
    - Schweitzer, Albert, 1957; photocopy (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 100)
    - Seelig, Arthur, 1953; photographs (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 100)
    - Serkin, Rudolf, 1946 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 100)
    - Seydel, Gerhard, 1957-1958; 1970 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 101)
    - Siepi, Cesare, 1953 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 102)
    - Skaupy, Walther, 1964; photographs (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 102)
    - Sonnenschein, Paul, Undated; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 102)
    - Stefansson, Vilhjalmur, 1954 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 102)
    - Stolzenberg, Ilse, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 102)
    - Szell, George, 1952 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 102)
    - Tel Aviv Museum, Jerusalem, 1969-1985; photographs (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 103)
    - Veit, Suse Abramczyk, 1964; photograph (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 104)
    - Vincenz, Hubert, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 104)
    - Walker, Betty, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 104)
    - Walter, Bruno, 1943 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 104)
    - Weber, Alfred, 1968; 1970 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 105)
    - Württemberg, Odo von, 1944 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 105)
  - Correspondence of Lilly Spiro, 1969-1985; 1.3
    - Abercron, Wilko von (Galerei von Abercron), 1978-1985 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 106)
    - Berlinische Galerie, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 107)
    - Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Marbach, 1978 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 108)
    - Galerie Wolfgang Ketterer, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 108)
    - Grether, Aloys, 1969; 1977-1979 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 108)
    - Gruber, Gerd, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 109)
    - Interdisciplinary Science Reviews (Anthony R. Michaelis re: Einstein photos), 1977-1978 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 110)
    - Jüdisches Museum, Ost-Berlin (Hermann Simon), 1983 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 111)
    - Die Künstlergilde e.V. (Schremmer), 1969-1977 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 112)
    - Liebrecht, Vera, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 113)
    - Max-Planck-Gesellschaft, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 114)
    - Mount Sinai Hospital, 1977 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 114)
    - Nathorff, Hertha, Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 114)
    - Ostdeutsche Galerie Regensburg, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 115)
    - Pfalzgalerie Kaiserslautern (Wilhelm Weber), 1973 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 115)
    - Rauter, Herbert (Consul), 1977-1978 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 116)
    - Schocken, Wolfgang A., 1982-1983 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 116)
    - Sieger, Henry, C.P.A., 1979-1983 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 116)
    - Smith, Dawn, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 117)
    - Smithsonian Institution, 1979 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 117)
    - Starck-Pauly, Ilse, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 117)
    - Stern, Isaac, 1976 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 118)
    - Three Lions Inc., Publishers (Max G. Lowenherz), 1975; 1977 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 118)
    - Universitätsbibliothek Düsseldorf (Thomas Mann Sammlung), 1977; 1980; photographs (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 118)
    - Condolence letters, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 119)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 120)
- Biographical materials and documents, Undated; 2; 4 file folders
  This series consists primarily of texts prepared by Eugen Spiro, including versions of curriculum vitae, short biographies, and lists of paintings for exhibits.
  - Biographical statements, incl. curriculum vitae, lists of portraits painted and exhibited, short biographical statements, lexicon entries, Undated (Box 2 (2-Biographical materials and documents), Folder 1)
  - Biographical statements about Spiro by others, incl. Ernst Freund, Max Osborn, Ernst Scheyer, Margarethe Steinberg, Undated (Box 2 (2-Biographical materials and documents), Folder 2)
  - Documents, ca. 1964 (Box 2 (2-Biographical materials and documents), Folder 3)
    Including death certificate, Grosse Verdienstkreuz.
  - Awards -- newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 2 (2-Biographical materials and documents), Folder 4)
- Writings of Eugen Spiro, 1932-1964; Undated; 3; 8 file folders